Guide to the Charles McKinney Papers, 1952-1993 and undated RL.00878
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Charles McKinney papers
1952-1993 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
McKinney, Charles C., 1931-2007
RL.00878
42 Linear Feet
Charles C. Chick McKinney founded and headed the McKinney & Silver (M&S) advertising agency for 22 years, where he held positions of President and Chief Executive Officer. The agency, originally based in Raleigh, N.C., and presently headquartered in Durham, N.C., is one of the largest advertising agencies in the Southeastern U.S. The Charles McKinney Papers cover the years 1952-1993, with the bulk of materials dating from 1968-1990, the period during which McKinney served as President and CEO of the McKinney & Silver (M&S) advertising agency. The collection primarily consists of correspondence, memoranda, clippings, M&S presentations to clients, proofs, speeches, reports, McKinney's handwritten drafts of advertising campaigns, and numerous brochures from graphic artists and design companies. The collection also includes films of advertising spots, slides for new business presentations, and many periodicals related to advertising and graphic design. Companies represented in the collection include American Drew; Bacardi Corporation; Bahamas; Barnett Banks; Benihana; Beatrice Foods Company; Bigelow-Sanford Carpet Company; Black & Decker Corporation; Braniff Airways; Brown & Forman Inc.; Brown & Williamson; Colours; Del Monte Corporation; Drackett; Dunlop Sport, GoodMark Foods, Inc.; Gravely; Homelite; Kingsdown; Mars, Inc.; North Carolina National Bank; North Carolina Travel and Tourism; Norweigan Cruise Line; PET Dairy; Piedmont Airlines, Inc.; Pillsbury Company; Pine State; Quincy's; Royal Caribbean Cruise Line; Tile Council of America; Travelmation; and USAir Group, Inc.
31500 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, original audiovisual materials are closed to researchers until use copies can be obtained.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Charles McKinney Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2008.
Biographical Note
Charles C. Chick McKinney was born in 1931 in Newdale, N.C., and raised in Spruce Pine, N.C. Between 1950-1952, he attended the University of Tennessee, where he majored in Industrial Management. He received a degree in Business Administration from the University of North Carolina's School of Business in 1957. McKinney began his career in 1957 at the J.T. Howard advertising agency in Raleigh, N.C.. There, he served as Creative Director and member of the board. In 1968, McKinney founded the McKinney & Silver advertising agency, and he served as President and Chief Executive Officer until 1990. The agency grew to one of the largest advertising agencies in the Southeastern U.S.
McKinney received over 500 major awards from creative and advertising competitions, and some of his work appeared in The One Show exhibit in New York City, the New York Advertising Club Show, the American Television Commercials Festival, and the Communication Arts Show. In 1973, an Ad Daily poll named one of the top creative people in America.
In addition, McKinney also served as a judge in many advertising competitions around the U.S., including for the Communication Arts competition in California. He was frequently asked to speak at business and industry group meetings, including for the Magazine Publishers Association. He also served as a trustee of the North Carolina Symphony, and was a member of the National Trust for Historic Preservation, the Sphinx Club, the Carolina Country Club and the Figure Eight Yacht Club, among others.
McKinney died Sept. 12, 2007 in Raleigh, N.C.
Collection Overview
The Charles McKinney Papers cover the years 1952-1993, with the bulk of materials dating from 1968-1990, the period during which McKinney served as President and CEO of the McKinney & Silver (M&S) advertising agency. The collection primarily consists of correspondence; memoranda; clippings; presentations to clients; proofs; speeches; reports; McKinney's handwritten drafts of advertising campaigns; and brochures from graphic artists and design companies. The collection also includes films and videocassettes of advertising spots, slides for new business presentations, and periodicals related to advertising and graphic design. Companies represented in the collection include American Drew; Bacardi Corporation; Bahamas Tourism; Barnett Banks; Benihana; Beatrice Foods Company; Bigelow-Sanford Carpet Company; Black & Decker Corporation; Braniff Airways; Brown & Forman Inc.; Brown & Williamson; Colours; Del Monte Corporation; Drackett; Dunlop Sport; GoodMark Foods, Inc.; Gravely; Homelite; Kingsdown; Mars, Inc.; North Carolina National Bank; North Carolina Travel and Tourism; Norweigan Cruise Line; PET Dairy; Piedmont Airlines, Inc.; Pillsbury Company; Pine State Dairy; Quincy's; Royal Caribbean Cruise Line; Tile Council of America; Travelmation; and USAir Group, Inc.; among others.
Many of the clippings and presentation drafts and fragments arrived unfoldered and interspersed throughout the collection. Complete presentation drafts were foldered by presentation title; presentation fragments and clippings were foldered as miscellaneous. Many of McKinney's drafts of advertising campaigns appeared in ruled notepads, often with clippings and additional sketched interleaved. Items attached to a particular notepad were foldered together and titled by subject and detached from cardboard backing. Legal sized notes were photocopied and reduced to letter size.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is arranged into eight series: General Files; Account Files; Competitive Files; New Business; Printed Materials; Writings and Speeches; Audiovisual Materials; and Oversize Materials. The General Files series contains files related to the running of the M&S office and files related to McKinney's personal and business affairs. The Account Files series contains files related to M&S's active accounts, as well as some general files and presentations containing sales reports for multiple accounts, market research, and miscellaneous clippings relating to M&S accounts. The Competitive Files series contains correspondence, printed materials, proofs and clippings related to competitive advertising agencies. The New Business series contains materials related to M&S's attempts to acquire new accounts. The Printed Materials series includes newsletters, promotional materials, periodicals, reports, and typographic manuals. The Writings and Speeches series contains speeches given by McKinney and other advertising executives at various events and also includes reports prepared by outside agencies on general advertising and business-related topics which McKinney used as reference material. The Audiovisual Materials series contains various formats of film, video and audiotape primarily of M&S advertising spots, as well as promotional films and presentation reels prepared by competitive agencies. The Oversize Materials series contains large format items removed from previous series of the collection, including charts, clippings, periodicals, brochures, newspapers and proofs.
Related Material
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections of the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives: Account Files Collection; Corporation Vertical Files; Advertising Vertical Files; and the Shirley F. Woodell Papers. Additional related material may be located in the Arthur Einstein Papers; the Garrett Orr Papers; Bates Worldwide, Inc. Records; the John Benjamin Harris Papers; the D'Arcy Masius Benton & Bowles Archives; the William E. Phillips Papers; the David B. McCall Papers; and the Warwick Baker O'Neill Records.
Advertising agencies -- United States -- North Carolina -- History -- 20th century; Advertising agencies -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Advertising campaigns -- United States -- North Carolina -- History -- 20th century; Advertising campaigns -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Advertising campaigns -- United States -- North Carolina -- Periodicals; Advertising campaigns -- United States -- Periodicals; Videocassettes; Advertising executives -- United States; Proofs (printed matter); Speeches; Photographs; Clippings (information artifacts); New business enterprises -- United States; Graphic design -- 1960-1980; Television advertising -- United States; Slides (photographs); Advertising executives -- United States -- North Carolina; Graphic arts -- United States -- Periodicals; Graphic arts -- United States; Advertising agencies -- United States; Advertising agencies -- United States -- North Carolina; Advertising -- Periodicals; Motion pictures (visual works); Advertising agencies -- Management; Barnett Banks; Bahamas. Ministry of Tourism; Bigelow-Sanford Carpet Company; Beatrice Foods Company; Braniff Airways; Black and Decker Corporation (Towson, Md.); Del Monte Corporation; Brown & Williamson; USAir (Firm); Royal Caribbean Cruise Line; Tile Council of America; Piedmont Airlines; Pillsbury Company; North Carolina National Bank; North Carolina. Travel and Tourism Division; McKinney, Charles C., 1931-2007; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; McKinney & Silver; Drackett Company; Homelite Corporation
- General Files, 1961-1990 and undated, 5 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains files related to the management of the McKinney & Silver office and files related to McKinney's personal and business affairs. Items are divided into four subseries. Administrative Files include office-wide policies, agency profiles, questionnaires, general income reports, press releases, as well as resumes of company employees. Clippings consist of newspaper, magazine and photocopied book excerpts gathered by McKinney and his acquaintances. Correspondence includes correspondence and internal memoranda written by McKinney and other agency employees. Personal Materials include photographs of McKinney, event-related memorabilia, as well as McKinney's business cards and personal stationery.
  - Administrative Files, 1961-1990 and undated
    Primarily includes information related to agency procedures such as billing, everyday operations, workflows, cost estimating, legal reviews, and office arrangement. Includes descriptions of the agency's philosophy and corporate profile. Also contains background information on agency employees, account assignments. Original folder titles were maintained and arranged alphabetically.
    - Account service, operating procedures and systems, 1961-1977 (Box 1)
    - Advertising agency agreement, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Agency employee resumes, undated (Box 1)
    - Agency income reports, 1983-1987 (Box 1)
    - Agency operating procedures, undated (Box 1)
    - Agency philosophy on research, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Agency plans of action, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Agency profile, undated (Box 1)
    - Agency prospectus, undated (Box 1)
    - Agency questionnaire responses
      - General, 1981 and undated (Box 1)
      - BMW questionnaire, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Agency resume, undated (Box 1)
    - Agency resume, approved quotes, undated (Box 1)
    - Agency situation summary, undated (Box 1)
    - Agency workflow, 1975-1984, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Billing policy, 1984 and undated (Box 2)
    - Billing reports, 1979, 1981 and undated (Box 2)
    - Employee manual, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Estimating procedure, undated (Box 2)
    - Floorplans, decoration, 1979 and undated (Box 2)
    - General agency agreement, undated (Box 2)
    - Legal review procedures, 1985 (Box 2)
    - McKinney resumes, undated (Box 2)
    - Media department, reorganization and account assignments, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Media reference manual, undated (Box 2)
    - Promotional reference guide, 1978, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Public relations, press releases, 1969-1990 (Box 2)
    - Team member manual, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Clippings, 1960-1990
    Contains newspaper and magazine clippings related to general advertising issues and to particular advertising agencies. Also includes photocopied excerpts of books on marketing, some of which were compiled as reference materials for M&S presentations. Original folder titles were mainatined where available. Items arriving in unfoldered stacks were foldered as miscellaneous.
    - General topics editorials, 1969-1975 (Box 3)
    - Marketing research, 1973-1975 and undated (Box 3)
    - McKinney, Silver & Rockett, 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1966-1990, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous business tips, 1969-1974 (Box 3)
    - Reference
      - Miscellaneous book excerpts, 1975 and undated (Box 3)
      - Presentation reference, 1960-1968 (Box 3)
      - Sales and marketing information systems, book excerpts, undated (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1990 and undated
    Contains correspondence and memoranda written between McKinney, other agency executives, potential clients, competitive agencies, prospective employees and sales solicitors. Includes McKinney's correspondence with officials in the University of North Carolina-Chapel Hill Business School, and with personal friends. Also includes correspondence related to a 1993 lawsuit involving Braniff Airways. Original folder titles were maintained where available. Items arriving loose were grouped as either General correspondence or Miscellaneous internal memoranda. Folders arranged alphabetically.
    - General, 1975-1979 (Box 3)
    - General, 1980-1990, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - General financial, 1977-1979 and undated (Box 4)
    - Braniff versus McKinney & Silver lawsuit, 1993 (Box 4)
    - Lemont consulting, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Tom McElligott, 1978-1981 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous internal memoranda, 1979-1990, 1 of 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous internal memoranda (continued), 1979-1990, 2 of 2 folders (Box 5)
    - One Club, 1983-1984 (Box 5)
    - Personal correspondence, 1980-1981 and undated (Box 5)
    - Prospective employees, 1975-1986 (Box 5)
    - Solicitations
      - Moskowitz-Jacobs, 1989 (Box 5)
      - Sales solicitations, 1974-1979 (Box 5)
    - UNC Business School correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 5)
  - Personal Materials, 1972-1973 and undated
    Contains photograph portraits of McKinney, McKinney's business cards and letterhead stationery and ephemera related to advertising events.
    - McKinney business cards and stationery, undated (Box 5)
    - Memorabilia, 1972-1973 and undated (Box 5)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 5)
- Account Files, 1968-1990 and undated, 17 boxes
  Contains files related to M&S's active accounts, as well as some general files and presentations containing sales reports for multiple accounts, market research, and miscellaneous clippings relating to M&S accounts. The bulk of the materials contain presentation scripts, advertising proofs, creative development plans and correspondence tailored to specific clients, including companies specializing in clothing, food, tobacco, liquor and travel. Contains especially extensive materials for Bacardi Corporation; Barnett Banks; Benihana; Braniff Airways; Brown & Forman Inc.; Brown & Williamson; Colours (clothing); GoodMark Foods, Inc. (including the Slim Jim line of products); Gravely (tractors); Kingsdown (mattresses); Mars, Inc.; North Carolina National Bank; Norweigan Cruise Line; PET Dairy; Piedmont Airlines; Pillsbury; Pine State Dairy; Royal Caribbean Cruise Line; Tile Council of America; and USAir Group, Inc.
  Also includes some presentations composed by competitive advertising agencies, including Daisy Outdoor Products (Bloom Agency); Jim Dandy Chunx Dog Food, Hanes; Orkin Exterminating Co.; Savannah Sugar Refining Co. (Cargill, Wilson & Acree); Leader Savings & Loan (McDonald & Little). Items arrived foldered. Original folder titles were maintained where available. Unfoldered or unlabeled items were foldered or labeled by account and type of material. Large format proofs were separated into the Oversize series.
  - General (Box 6)
    - Banking accounts, 1973 and undated (Box 6)
    - Client status reports, 1976, 1980, 1982 and undated (Box 6)
    - Creative briefs, 1989 and undated (Box 6)
    - Local markets report, undated (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous proofs and tearsheets, 1982-1989 (Box 6)
    - Services schedule, 1982-1983 and undated (Box 6)
    - Slide presentations, undated (Box 6)
    - Snack market accounts presentation, undated (Box 6)
    - Table of sales, 1968-1979 (Some items removed to Oversize Materials) (Box 6)
    - 1984 accounts, 1984 (Box 6)
  - American Drew
    - Current marketing concept, 1974 (Box 6)
    - Media programs, 1978 (Box 6)
    - Memos and correspondence, 1972-1978 (Box 6)
    - Sales meetings, 1974-1975 (Box 6)
    - Sales presentation, 1976 (Box 6)
  - American Olean Tile Company
    - Presentation, 1975 (Box 6)
  - Bacardi (Box 7)
    - Añejo presentation, 1989 (Box 7)
    - Creative development presentation, 1989 (Box 7)
    - Creative development presentation draft, undated (Box 7)
    - New product creative presentation, 1989 (Box 7)
    - Proofs, undated, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Bahamas
    - Creative presentation, 1987 (Box 7)
    - Memos and correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 7)
    - Proofs, undated (Box 7)
  - Barnett Banks
    - Agency position summary, undated (Box 7)
    - Creative input report, 1977 program, 1976 (Box 7)
    - Creative presentation, undated (Box 7)
    - Creative recommendation, 1973 (Box 7)
    - Marketing direction, 1975 (Box 7)
    - Memos and correspondence, 1972-1984 (Box 7)
    - Newspaper ad campaign, 1976-1977 (Box 7)
    - Presentation cards, undated (Box 8)
    - Presentation drafts, undated (Box 8)
    - Program for deposit acquisition, 1976-1977 (Box 8)
    - Proofs, undated (Box 8)
    - Strategic planning meetings, 1981-1982 (Box 8)
  - Beatrice Foods
    - Advertising agency agreement, 1973, 1976 (Box 8)
  - Benihana
    - Advertising agency agreement, 1984 (Box 8)
    - Creative options, undated (Box 8)
    - Creative presentation, 1983 (Box 8)
    - Laying Down the Tracks presentation, 1983 (Box 8)
    - Packaging photos, undated (Box 8)
    - Scripts, 1984 (Box 8)
  - Bigelow-Sanford Carpet Company
    - Creative presentation, 1977 (Box 8)
  - Black & Decker
    - Confidential briefing report, undated (Box 8)
    - Memos and correspondence, 1981-1987 (Box 8)
    - New business conference reports, 1986 (Box 9)
    - Proofs, undated (Box 9)
    - Storyboards, undated (Box 9)
  - Bost Breads
    - Creative presentations, undated (Box 9)
    - Positioning strategy, 1986 (Box 9)
  - Braniff Airlines
    - Commuter map changes, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Flight attendant ad, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Inaugural certificates, 2 versions, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Kansas City Chiefs outdoor campaign, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Kids Fly Free campaign, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Leisure fares, Pin Down a Low Fare, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Orlando outdoor, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Print ad authorizations, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Proof book, 1989 (Box 9)
    - September Spotlight magazine ad, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Telephone call reports, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Travel agent spread, Middle of America, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Wilford Brimley, travel agent, television campgain, 1989 (Box 9)
  - Brown-Forman Spirits
    - Agency presentation, 1981, 1984, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Presentation, How We Would Approach An Assignment for Brown-Forman, 1981 (Box 9)
    - Proposal, 1984 (Box 9)
  - Brown & Williamson (Box 10)
    - Aries
      - Flip charts, undated (Box 10)
      - Marketing research, 1985 (Box 10)
      - Outdoor boards, 1984 (Box 10)
      - Presentation script, version 1, 1984 (Box 10)
      - Presentation script, version 2, 1984 (Box 10)
      - Proofs, undated (Box 10)
    - Copy direction, undated (Box 10)
    - Flip charts, undated (Box 10)
    - Marketing charts, undated (Box 10)
    - Memos and correspondence, 1979-1985 (Box 10)
    - New chewing tobaccos positioning strategy, 1980 (Box 10)
    - New Moist positioning strategy, 1980 (Box 10)
    - Novelas target audience, undated (Box 10)
    - Presentation, general, 1978 (Box 10)
    - Presentation, Managing the Smokeless Tobacco Business, undated (Box 10)
    - Presentation outline, 1985 (Box 10)
  - Casa Gallardo
    - Statement of M&S billing policy and services, 1979 (Box 10)
  - Cellular One
    - Advertising agency briefing plan, 1987 (Box 10)
  - Central National Bank
    - Final presentation, 1975 (Box 10)
    - Presentation script, 1975 (Box 10)
  - Ceramic Tile (Box 11)
    - Presentation notes, undated (Box 11)
  - Chattem Laboratories
    - Skin type surveys, 1976 and undated (Box 11)
  - Chick-Fil-A
    - Presentation notes, undated (Box 11)
  - Chloride, Inc.
    - Capabilities presentation, 1976 (Box 11)
  - CIBA-GEIGY
    - Proposal, 1985 (Box 11)
  - Clark
    - Proofs, undated (Some items removed to Oversize Materials) (Box 11)
  - Colours
    - General files, 1984 and undated (Box 11)
    - Charts for marketing presentation, 1984 (Box 11)
    - Cluett, Peabody & Co. presentation, 1984 (Box 11)
    - Marketing presentation script draft, 1984 (Box 11)
    - Positioning paper, undated (Box 11)
    - Positioning strategy sketches, undated (Box 11)
    - Presentation notes, undated (Box 11)
    - Presentation script, 1984 (Box 11)
    - Presentation script draft, undated (Box 11)
    - Proofs, undated (Box 11)
  - Conwood Corporation
    - Presentation, 1975 (Box 11)
  - Daisy Outdoor Products, Air Guns
    - Bloom Agency, marketing strategy recommendations, 1972 (Box 11)
  - DeLorean Motor Company
    - Presentation, 1979 (Box 11)
  - Del Monte Corporation
    - Presentation, 1986 (Box 11)
    - [Proofs removed to Oversize Materials] (Box 11)
  - Drackett
    - New product proposal draft, undated (Box 11)
    - New Solid Diet Product Concept for Weight Reduction, undated (Box 11)
    - Presentation, 1976 (Box 12)
  - Dunlop Sport
    - Preliminary 1980-1981 media program, 1980 (Box 12)
    - Presentation script, 1980 (Box 12)
  - Econocar International
    - Presentation, undated (Box 12)
  - Farm Best Dairy
    - Presentation, 1975 (Box 12)
  - GoodMark Foods, Inc.
    - Advertising planning guidelines, 1975 (Box 12)
    - Consumer communications, 1974-1978 (Box 12)
    - Consumer program, 1977-1978 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence, 1973-1980 (Box 12)
    - Divisional presidents' meeting, undated (Box 12)
    - Jesse Jones
      - City Slickers Guide to Selling Country Sausage, undated (Box 12)
      - Presentation, undated (Box 12)
      - Sales figures, 1974-1976 (Box 12)
    - Marketing plan, 1977-1978 (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous presentations, 1975 and undated (Box 12)
    - New products, 1974 (Box 12)
    - New product proposal, 1976, copy 1, 1-2 of 4 folders (Box 12)
    - New product proposal (continued), 1976, 3-4 of folders (Box 13)
    - Pemican Beef Jerky
      - Name and positioning recommendation, 1977 (Box 13)
      - Notes, undated (Box 13)
    - Printed materials, 1975-1977 and undated (Box 13)
    - Proposed relationship, 1973 (Box 13)
    - Review of Roper Reports, 1975-1978 (Box 13)
    - Slim Jim
      - Marketing plan, 1976-1977 (Box 13)
      - Priority problem evaluation, undated (Box 13)
      - Proofs and sketches, undated (Box 13)
      - Strategic planning model, undated (Box 13)
  - Gravely
    - General files, 1979 and undated (Box 13)
    - Agency evaluation system, 1975 (Box 13)